<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace in the Ile of Ree, containing these particulars The strong siedge of the French King before the towne of Rochell. The state of the towne of Rochell, with the demolishing of the new fort, which the Kings brother was building vpon the point Blanchine, by the Rochellers. The state of the English army vnder the conduct of the Duke of Buckingham. The surprising of nine boates of the enemies, which would have releeued the fort. The French in the fort driuen vnto a parley. The new supplies of the fort. The now state of the fort with the surpizing [sic] of the outworkes of the same. The supplies the Rochellers haue sent vnto the Duke. The funerall of Sir Iohn Borrowes. With many other occurences of note. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846856</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1043:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace in the Ile of Ree, containing these particulars The strong siedge of the French King before the towne of Rochell. The state of the towne of Rochell, with the demolishing of the new fort, which the Kings brother was building vpon the point Blanchine, by the Rochellers. The state of the English army vnder the conduct of the Duke of Buckingham. The surprising of nine boates of the enemies, which would have releeued the fort. The French in the fort driuen vnto a parley. The new supplies of the fort. The now state of the fort with the surpizing [sic] of the outworkes of the same. The supplies the Rochellers haue sent vnto the Duke. The funerall of Sir Iohn Borrowes. With many other occurences of note. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Eagle and Childe in Britaines-Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Nouember 2.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1592-1628.</term>
               <term>Ré Expedition, 1627 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11850:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11850:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nouember</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>A Continued IOVRNALL OF ALL THE PROCEEDINGS of the Duke of BVCKINGHAM his Grace in the Ile of <hi>Ree,</hi> containing <hi>theſe particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The ſtrong Siedge of the <hi>French</hi> King before the Towne of <hi>Rochell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtate of the Towne of <hi>Rochell,</hi> with the demoliſhing of the new Fort, which the Kings Brother was building vpon the point <hi>Blanchine,</hi> by the <hi>Rochellers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtate of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army vnder the Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſurpriſing of nine Boates of the Enemies, which would haue releeued the Fort.</item>
               <item>The <hi>French</hi> in the Fort driuen vnto a Parley.</item>
               <item>The new Supplies of the Fort.</item>
               <item>The now ſtate of the Fort with the ſurpizing of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes of the ſame.</item>
               <item>The ſupplies the <hi>Rochellers</hi> haue ſent vnto the Duke.</item>
               <item>The Funerall of Sir <hi>Iohn Borrowes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>With many other occurrences of note.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Walkley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Eagle</hi> and <hi>Childe</hi> in <hi>Britaines Burſſe.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11850:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11850:2"/>
            <head>THE IOVRNALL CONTINVED TO <hi>THIS DAY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Continued to</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>of Nouember.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my laſt <hi>Iournall</hi> of aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Duke of BVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KINGHAMS <hi>Excellencie,</hi> in the Ile <hi>Ree,</hi> which ſaid <hi>Iournall</hi> was dated on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>October</hi> laſt. I related vnto you the eſtate of our Leaguer as it then ſtood, with diuers particulars, concerning the Fort of <hi>Saint Martins,</hi> and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiedging of <hi>Rochell</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> Army. Since which time there are two ſeuerall Meſſengers arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in <hi>England,</hi> whoſe relation concerning the <hi>French</hi> affaires, both in the Maine, and in the Iland, is as followeth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King is now perſonally come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Towne of <hi>Rochell,</hi> being willing to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11850:3"/>the Siedge with his preſence. Before his comming his brother the <hi>Monſieur</hi> had vſed all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes to annoy the Towne, being furniſhed with all Materialls and Engines fit for ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>He lyes ſtrongly intrenched, and hath a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and numerous Army, as being aboue thirty Thouſand thought by the Liſt.</p>
            <p>He plies the Towne with his Canon day and night, and hath burned ſome houſes, with Wilde fire Balles, Granadoes, and other fiery Miſſiues, which the Beſiedgers ſhoot into the Towne, for the moſt part, in the night time, out of their Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards and morter Peeces.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rochellers</hi> notwithſtanding this, make a braue and reſolute reſiſtance, and haue made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe couragious Sallies, in which they haue taken and ſlaine many of the braueſt <hi>French Caualiers.</hi> And that they might make the Beſiedgers know, how little they doe eſteeme that great Army, they haue by way of open defiance vnto the <hi>French,</hi> hung vp the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Colours vpon the walles.</p>
            <p>They haue ſo plyed the the newe Fort (which the <hi>French</hi> King is building vpon the point before <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell</hi>) with their Cannon, that they haue quite ſleighted and ruined the Fortifications of it, and haue ſlaine ſundry perſons of quallity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande in the <hi>French</hi> Kings Army.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces which beſiedge the Fort of Saint <hi>Martins,</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Ree,</hi> vnder the conduct
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11850:3"/>of his Illuſtrious Excellency, the Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> haue deliuered vnto the World braue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their valour and patience, being as well couraged in ſuffering, as actiue in doing, thinking no labour too difficult, nor danger to perrillous, where the honour of their Countrey, and their proper duty is engaged.</p>
            <p>They haue brought their approaches cloſe to the Enemies Counterskarfe, though not without ſweat, and bloud, there hauing beene made diuers braue Skirmsſhes by them, and diuers braue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts by vs.</p>
            <p>And as it is reported by a <hi>Duchman,</hi> who came lately to the Court, our men haue beaten the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies out of all their outworkes, ſo that both the Counterskarfes and the Skonſe without the Fort being loſt, there remaines nothing vnconquered, but the Cittadell it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe Out-workes, as this Meſſenger relateth, are poſſeſſed by Colonell <hi>Gray,</hi> a man that knowes how to keepe his footing, as well as any Souldier in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>This report is likely to be true, as being deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon perill of his credit, yet another Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that came thence foure dayes before this <hi>Dutchman,</hi> and arriued at the Court, the ſame night that the other did (hauing beene hindred in his iourney by meanes of a wracke) cannot, and will not aſſure as much.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Excellency</hi> before the arriuall of Sir <hi>William Beacher</hi> with new Supplies of Men, Munition, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11850:4"/>Victualls, ſuffered much, both in his owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and in the generalitie, and was faine to giue the common Soldiers out of his owne ſtore, to keepe them from mutining, and for continuing them in their duties.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soldiers doe much dutie, as wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching by turnes euery ſecond or thirde night in the Trenches, which bringes ſome of them into fluxes, feuers and other diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Beſides, they were ſo much diſtreſſed for want of Victualls before the comming of the laſt ſupplies, in ſo much that eight Men were put to fower Mens allowance.</p>
            <p>Yet this want was in part relieued by the ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of nine <hi>French</hi> Veſſells or Shallops laden with Victualls, which intended (if they could) to relieue the Fort.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there ariued happely a Shippe of <hi>Briſtow,</hi> which being laden with Victualls, did for a time relieue our Armie.</p>
            <p>To ſecond which good fortune, Sir <hi>William Beecher</hi> ariued happily and ſafely, with all requiſite and neceſſarie Prouiſions, which did much refreſh our Men, and relieue our neceſſities.</p>
            <p>Neither were the beſiedged without their ſhare of wantes, but were troubled with them more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and preſsingly, ſo that they ſent to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie to parlie, and were reſolued to ſurrender vp the Fort.</p>
            <p>But as they were treating vpon Conditions, there hapned a ſtorme that night, it being then a Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11850:4"/>by the benefit whereof, they did put into the Fort ſome ſmall proportion of Victualls.</p>
            <p>But yet this was but a drop throwne into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of their wants, and like a Squibbe tyed vnto a Bulls taile, it encreaſed their appetite and our anger.</p>
            <p>For although this deſperat aduenture furniſhed them with ſome proportion for the preſent: yet there penurie is growne as preſſing as before, and as the <hi>Dutchman</hi> reporteth, thoſe of the Fort are againe much diſtreſſed, ſo that want makes ſome ſicke, and many Fugitiues.</p>
            <p>Through whoſe defect there are not aboue fiue hundred of the beſiedged left in the Fort, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are ſo weake, that they cannot ſtand vnder Pike or Musket.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> (Monſieur <hi>Subeza</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) hath readie 7000. Foote, and 500. Horſe, well prouided and braue Soldiers in a readines, for the ayde of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>The Pope doth endeauor all he can to make this quarrell belong to the Emperour, the K. of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> perſwading them it is for Religion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rochelers</hi> haue fully declared themſelues for the King of <hi>England,</hi> to which agreement, there are diuers Articles concluded on by his Excellence.</p>
            <p>His Excellence hath ſent word to his Maieſtie, that if it will pleaſe him to ſend him Bread he will deſerue it, but if he will adde vnto it ſomething more he will drinke his Health.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11850:5"/>
            <p>Our men haue mounted their Cannon ſo aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagiouſly, that they command the Enemies Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and haue diſmounted them our of their Carriages, ſo that they haue not one Peece left to play vpon the Approaches, either from their Batteries, or Caſemates.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> knowing how much the honour of their Nation, and the ſafety of the neighbouring Prouinces on the firme Land depends vpon the keeping of the Fort, haue ſought againe to releeue it with ſixteene Boates, but being diſcouered by our men, they were purſued by our Long Boatse, Shallops, and thoſe flatt bottomd Boates, with which the <hi>Rochellers</hi> haue furniſhed vs, being Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels very ſeruiceable both for chaſe and fight.</p>
            <p>Wee ſuncke foure of theſe Barques, the reſt got into the Maine and by the benefit of their Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legges eſcaped our hands.</p>
            <p>The enemies neuer attempt to releeue the Fort but in a ſtormy night, and Spring-Tide, and then our Ships were of little vſe in reſpect of the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night.</p>
            <p>We haue no other meanes of hinderance, or preuention, but by the Boates and Shallops afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>There runnes away dayly many Souldiers out of the Fort vnto our Leaguer, notwithſtanding all the care and perſwaſions of the Gouernour.</p>
            <p>Theſe are not ſent into the Maine, but kept in the Iſland vnder ſafe cuſtody, becauſe they ſhall not carry any meſſage, nor deliuer any particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceruing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11850:5"/>our Affaires.</p>
            <p>Theſe Fugitiues informe vs, by a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of report, that the Beſiedged are compelled to ſuſtaine nature with things vnnaturall, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſuall to the Pallate: their greateſt daineties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but bread and water, and they are allowed that but in a ſmall proportion. So that they hold it for certaine, that vpon the arriuall of our next Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, the <hi>French</hi> will foorthwith ſurrender the Fort.</p>
            <p>I pray God they may come thither ſafely and opportunely, and then in humane reaſon, we haue no reaſon to doubt of good ſucceſſe; for if the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiedgers do not giue vp the Fort by that time vpon compoſition, his <hi>Excellencie,</hi> by Gods aſſiſtance, will aduenture to make a forcible entrie, He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right well in the cleareneſſe of his iudgement, that the Defendants are ſo fewe and weake, that they cannot endure a generall Aſſault.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, our men intrench themſelues to preuent the excurſions &amp; ſallies of the Enemies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> doe earneſtly mediate for quarter at Sea, but his <hi>Excellence</hi> well knowing that no reliefe can come to the Fort but by water, will not grant them any quarter at all.</p>
            <p>But to deterre the Enemies from bringing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and to hinder their deſperate attempts, all thoſe which fall into our Sea-mens hands, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put to the Sword, hanged vp to the maine Yeard, or throwne ouerboard.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rochellers</hi> hauing no other Victualls but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11850:6"/>what is tranſported vnto them from other places, and being doubtfull to be neceſſitated themſelues, haue affoorded vs as yet no great reliefe, onely they haue exchanged ſome meale for bread corne, and haue taken One Thouſand of our ſickemen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Towne, and inſteed of them haue ſent ouer to vs fiue Hundred of their owne Souldiers to fill vp our numbers, vntill the comming of the next Supplie.</p>
            <p>His Excelencie in the continuation of this Siedge hath taken more then ordinarie paines and care, ſparing his perſon from no labour nor perill, in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the preſent ſeruice: And although he hath hitherto been doubtfully ſupplyed out of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of the contrary winds, and the delayes which happen commonly in ſuch great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet he hath ſubdued theſe difficulties with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible patience, and hath wonne an honorable reputation amongſt all the Souldiers of our Nation.</p>
            <p>For knowing that the vertue of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> is che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by nothing more then by the loue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their Commanders, he is wanting neither in the one or the other, but with his preſence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts them in their night duties, and by viſiting and relieuing the ſicke and wounded, obliedgeth the hearts of his Soldiers vnto him.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this out of any fawning or partiality, (trueth being neerer to me then the Duke of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham,</hi>) but only to make thoſe know (who out of priuate reſpects haue been maleuolent againſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11850:6"/>him) how much they haue wronged his merit and reputation.</p>
            <p>And although diuers men who are either affected to the <hi>French,</hi> or diſaffected to his Excellencie, haue held the taking of the Fort of Saint <hi>Martines</hi> a thing more then difficult, as being altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; and haue made the Siedge the ſubiect of their ieſts and table talke: Yet if in ſerene and more impartiall iudgements, we ſhall conſider the cauſes for which this enterpriſe was vndertaken, and the meanes which doe facilitate and aſſure the taking of the Fort, we cannot chuſe but alow the deſigne (although diuers of theſe prepoſſeſſed Spirits haue cenſured the contrarie) for honorabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, profitable and feaſable, being grounded vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he neceſſities of Policie and Religion.</p>
            <p>I know that it hath been reported, and hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the vulgar ſwallow (I meane thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho are of vulgar apprehenſions,) that his Excelencie before <hi>Beechers</hi> arriuall, diſpaired of ſucceſſe, and had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Siedge, if he had not receiued ſpeedie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of victualls.</p>
            <p>This report may be true, without any blemiſh to his Excellencie, ſince no warlike enterpriſe can haue his due proceeding, without Men, Money, Munition and Victualls, which are the meanes of an actiue motion.</p>
            <p>But ſince that time, the Siedge hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with a powerfull hand, new ſupplies are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued out of <hi>England;</hi> and the ſuccours vnder the conduct of the Earles of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11850:7"/>vpon their paſſage towards the Iſland: Whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall (I hope) will crowne his Excellencies head with the wreath of Succeſſe, and the lawrell of Victorie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Relation of the Funerall ſolemnitie of that Honorable Knight, Sir <hi>Iohn Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,</hi> who was interred at <hi>Weſtmiſter,</hi> on Teweſday the 23. of October. <hi>1627.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ON teweſday, being the 23. of October, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of that Honorable Knight Sir <hi>Iohn Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi> (who being Colonell Generall of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Infanterie in the Iſle of <hi>Ree,</hi> was ſlaine with a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket ſhotte from the Fort) was brought from <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Houſe to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abbey, where neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tombe of Sir <hi>Francis Veare</hi> (whoſe Pupill he had been in the art of Warre) it was interred, with great funerall pompe, and with ſuch Rites as were due to his deſerts.</p>
               <p>To ſolemnize his Obſequies, fiue Companies of of the Citie of <hi>London</hi> were drawne into Armes, being about twelue hundred in number, who mart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before the Corpes with their Cullours, Pikes and Muskets trailed.</p>
               <p>The Pike which he recouered with his Sword and Target from the <hi>Frenchman</hi> vpon our firſt landing (who charged him with it at the puſh, and razed the skinne with the point of it thorough his breeches) was carried aduanced before, with his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11850:7"/>owne Enſigne trayled, and his Horſe for Seruice clad in mourning blacke.</p>
               <p>Next to the Horſe, there went ſixe and fiftie old Soldiers, with black Caſſockes, Swords and Staues, being as many in number as he was yeares old.</p>
               <p>His Scutcheon, Sword, Gauntlets and Spurres, were carried by the Heraulds. His Brother was Chiefe-mourner, being accompanied with twoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principall Mourners.</p>
               <p>Next vnto theſe, went the Earles of <hi>Dorſet, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, Carlile, Barkeſhire,</hi> and <hi>Molgraue;</hi> The Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>Grandiſon Conway,</hi> and <hi>Wimbleton,</hi> with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other Knightes and Gentlemen of qualitie.</p>
               <p>In the middeſt of the Abbey Church, a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Quite, there was a ſtately Herſe erected, which is yet ſtanding, couered ouer with blacke Veluet, where his Corpes was placed during the time of the Sermon, which was preached by Mr. <hi>Adams,</hi> a learned and renerent Diuine.</p>
               <p>Vpon his Hearſe his Scutchions were fixed, with this Motto, <hi>Nec inſiſto paruis.</hi> which in Engliſh is thus <hi>I doe not dwell vpon low things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sermon being ended, and Offerings being made, his Bodie was interred, and as it was put into the earth, the Muskatiers of thoſe fine Companies honoured his Interment with three vollies of ſhot, their Coullers diſplaied, and their Drumbes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, his owne Enſigne was broken and buried with him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Journall.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11850:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11850:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
